[Music]
we sat for a moment at the emergence of
systems of justification and we've kind
of got a little bit of a handle on
what's up there
together like now we're getting into
this shared space
and we can kind of fast forward so now
we've got cultural evolution
you know right step one humans exit the
role of apex predator and or start
playing a totally different game
step two they start playing that game
against each other we can focus on that
if we like
right um and maybe game a yeah
exactly game a that's right exactly
um and then and then we enter into where
we are now right
which is we're reaching the the end of
that
phase into that exact stage so okay
what's so let's talk about that so you
talked about the digital
so let's do the same thing let's zoom
into the the tail end
of the culture game and then
the emergence of the new thing exactly
okay
so um let's at least let's ground
ourselves about where we are
so we can have a nice frame for what we
can be talking about what's very
difficult to talk about given
what we don't know is coming right um so
so in the tree of knowledge the tree of
knowledge says following matter
life mind and culture are such radically
different planes of existence
okay because what emerges is a
coordinating system
of information processing and
communication networks
that coordinate the flow of energy to
give rise to more and more
complex structure yep okay
so cells store information rna dna
they they process that inside their
lipid membrane and then communicate with
each other okay
then you jump up to animals and nervous
systems yoke cells together
coordinate the animal of the whole and
then animals communicate to each other
okay then when we started
jiving in our gestural
symbolic way and then linked into
propositions
created the inner subjective language
highway that yoked our subjective minds
together to create the culture person
plane
okay so the medium to marshall mcluhan
the medium is absolutely central right
um
and ever since we started writing so
what we started to do with writing
we started to create an externalized
memory of our
symbolic language okay so we
externalized our memory
and then we stored that and created
better and better systems
so that other people could then process
that when they learned how to read
and develop printing presses and then we
developed computational systems on
quantitative things like an abacus
and then turn that into a babbage
thinking machine right
and then in the twentieth centuries
developed the silicon chip
we developed the internet we developed
artificial intelligence and can yoke
them together
what does that all mean we have created
a whole new information processing
system in communication network
okay out of material culture so we built
all these material cultural things our
technologies
but now we've created an independent or
at least interfacing
artificial intelligence network so now
there is
information processing communication
taking place in just a radically
different way
that's my term you know many people use
the term digital
okay so the digital so now
that's why the tree of knowledge says
very clearly we're going to be in a flux
point
okay it's like it's like we it's like
what happened when we just discovered
propositions we have now just discovered
digital and yoking digital and
interfacing with digital
and creating the whole digital
interconnected internet
so we're on the cusp where we were at
the fourth joint point we're now on the
cusp of the fifth
and we're now just opening up like we
use propositions now we're opening up
digital interface spaces okay so
something like we discover the
interest objective space and we begin
exploring how to do it good yep
and we notice that there's a number of
basic boundary conditions
right one boundary condition is how much
intersubjective space can you hold
yep i'm limited to the boundaries of
human memory there's a certain limit
to the amount of intersubjective space
that can be can be generated
right um therefore we begin the process
of trying to
cybernetically enhance memory and we
discover that if we
externalize memory into
physical reality writing
then we have expanded that capacity and
therefore can build much larger
inter-subjective spaces which as you say
also requires the
creative new particular skills and
capacities like literacy
and probably cognitive structures for
being able to do
translations between languages and being
able to
run higher level abstractions to verify
the
epistemology has to get stronger as you
start having more
ambiguity built into the symbolic
structure just trying to map the inner
subjective space
we also have notions about velocity like
as you said in distance
right if the only way for me to read the
book is i've got to travel to milan by
wagon that's you know it's a it slows
down the ability for us to share their
subjective space which is basically the
end of the day a bandwidth issue
so if i can ramp up the bandwidth by
virtue of being able to call somebody or
talk with somebody or if i can just do a
video call over zoom the
velocity of information exchange goes
way up
so i can now in the in the context of
digital
we're reaching something along the lines
of a
it feels like it's it's interesting to
think about the quantitative qualitative
shift at the quantitative level
so on this side of the transition it's
just like
moore's law like the thing we've been
doing for 70 000 years
we're just doing more of it faster lots
and lots and lots
so memory is expanding like doubling
every year remember that yep
and velocity is increasing and the
number of
interactions that can happen is
increasing and the reification capacity
to do the
checksum at the epistemological level is
increasing in spite of the false
news fake news problem which we're going
to probably have to get to
in this conversation then you've got
this notion of a
qualitative shift and that's where
things get
real tricky right right that implies
something which is not the same as
person right and not the same as culture
no all of person and all of culture live
below the line so whatever we're talking
about on the other side of the line
ain't person and it ain't culture
yep right so that and that is
so you have a novel information
processing system and the way a silicon
chip processes information right and
then we build
so now our what i mean we used to have
you know rocks
hammers build houses but now we build
things that actually process information
computers on their own right and then
they get more
and more learning mechanisms and then
they get more interface we call that
artificial intelligence of course
and and whether it's artificial
intelligence on its own like ray
kurzweil thinks
or like i think which is really going to
be artificial intelligence interfacing
with human intelligence
and as our human capacity increases and
we neural link as
elon musk was talking you know but we
build
the information processing of our
capacity to plug into the internet
okay um uh it just the opening
of that interface is
like we're like jellyfish right before
they got
brains you know you got a distributed
neural net
right and then you've got a control
center system and then boom all of a
sudden you can move the whole goddamn
system
so we have distributed and it's getting
more and more centralized
and whatever that tipping point is going
to be is going to launch us into the
digital
and that's what we're staring at here at
the 21st century this is this is why the
blue church is so inadequate because
it's built on radically different
information processing communication
sense making systems that are now
inadequate to manage uh what we've
opened up
right and i think we can actually begin
the process of making
fundamental statements of what adequate
looks like
yeah that's where things get interesting
we can actually start defining the
parameter space
it's like look i don't know what's going
to be on the other side of that line but
i know for sure it's going to have to
have this set of parameters
exactly and i'm not sure oh go ahead
okay i was just talking with a
philosophical friend we were talking
about well
we can't know what it is but he used the
uh analogy well we can midwife it
okay that is that we can put constraints
on it and then we can think about
what is adequate to see coming down the
pike and how to hold it in a way so that
chaos and order and and framings are
structured well there's a simple one
right i can give you one very simple
parameter
if it if if it if it kills everybody
then it's outside of the parameter space
i think we can start there
right if it results in the extinction of
all life
outside the parameters it's certainly
our prerequisite space but that's
actually the
point there is actually i think that
let's drill deeper on that because i
think
this uh the there's something deeper
there yeah
absolutely when we were and and and
exiting eden
is is the hint right so there was a that
we had a moment
where we had this uh this thing that was
coming up
that had to use john's language it was
at the level of participatory knowing
right
relevance realization something that is
grounded all the way down
to 13 billion years of evolution right
all the way down with continuity
right no discontinuity then we have this
leaving of eden which
has a discontinuity and we somehow exit
that
to come into propositional space which
is a different kind of thing
right then and the two are you know
you're you're as you said you're you're
a primate you're still a primate
and you're a person right but there's a
discontinued between person and primate
and we try to keep them linked sometimes
sometimes we don't sometimes we engage
in all kinds of crazy in person
space that is absolutely out of
alignment with our primates nature
which generally makes us unhappy in the
long term but it might make us happy in
the short term
tell ourselves lies like crazy um
so
the proposition that
that digital that total that set of
digital
that extinguishes all life is outside
the parameter space
is another way of saying that the
discontinuity
between the propositional and the
participatory is outside the parameter
space
that the digital must must of necessity
be connected must be in continuity with
the whole evolutionary story exactly
exactly so and that's why i like to call
it
the digital metacultural transcendent
okay what i hope for and what i mean by
that is
the constraints of the emerging digital
okay need to be connected to the root
from metacultural down into cultural
into mind into life
yeah and you know and and the wise way
if we do it wisely we open up heaven
and if we do it right and that's the and
that's the
you know and by the way that's the whole
metaphor of from the tree of knowledge
into the garden
okay is a return to the garden
all right uh that allows for
if we get it right if we get it wisely
done
um we can align across and
and return to paradise
[Music]
you